A Guide to the Clifford Lewis III Papers, 1639-1995
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Clifford Lewis III Papers, 1639-1995.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 2000.99
3,301 items.
Clifford Lewis III.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Clifford Lewis III, a native of Pennsylvania, was a stockbroker by occupation, a historian by avocation. He married twice, first to Mary Butler (d.1970). After her death, he married Virginia Gibson Bullitt (d.1979).
Scope and Content Information
Research materials compiled by Clifford Lewis III (b.1904-d. 2000), including notebooks containing summaries of his research; publications which resulted from Lewis's research and correspondence concerning his publications; photographs and negatives of research sites and family members; materials regarding his research related affiliations; also, correspondence with researchers, libraries and booksellers, family members.
Organization
This collection has been organized into 7 series:
Series 1. Affiliations
Series 2. Correspondence
Series 3. Research Notebooks
Series 4. Photographs and Negatives
Series 5. Publications
Series 6. Research Materials
Series 7. Oversize Materials
Index Terms
Family Names:
Plowden family.
Persons:
Lewis, Clifford.; Plowden, Edmund, Sir, 1590-1659.
Subjects:
Indians of North America (East, U.S.)
Geographical Names:
Delaware--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600- 1775.; Maryland--History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; New York (State)-- History--Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
Contents List
- Affiliations, 1933-1992., 5 folders. (Box-folder 1:1-1:5)
  Lewis's affiliation with the following organizations is documented in this series: Maryland Historic Trust (1974-1989), Maryland Historical Society (1933-35), St. Mary's County (Maryland) Historic Society (1975-1992), and The Society of Architectural Historians (1956-1975).
  - Maryland Historic Trust, 1974-1989., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Includes correspondence, an annual report, a brochure, and newsletters.
  - Maryland Historical Society, 1933-1935., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
    Includes correspondence and a magazine.
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1940. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Includes certificates and an invitation.
  - St. Mary's County Historic Society, 1975-1992., 2 items. (Folder 1:4)
    Includes a magazine and research information.
  - Society of Architectural Historians, 1956-1975., 13 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Includes a magazine and conference materials.
- Correspondence, 1927-1991., 10 folders. (Box-folder 1:6-1:15)
  This series contains correspondence between Lewis and various researchers and research institutions, and family members. Primary correspondents included: Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. (1953-1954), Burford Butcher (1936-1937), Lucy Drucker (1937-1940), Margaret Franklin (1965-66), Peter Guilday and William Kelley, (1941-1960), Mary Hoss Headman (1933-1937), F.H.T. Jervoise (1939-1956), Walter J. Kaye (1934), Philip C. Plowden (1932-1969), and Hilda S. Reid (1935-36).
  Arranged alphabetically by major correspondent with miscellanous correspondence and some financial records at the end.
  - Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. correspondence, 1953-1954. (Box-folder 1:6)
    Correspondence, notes concerning Beauchamp Plantagenet research.
  - Burford Butcher correspondence, 1936-1937., 9 items. (Folder 1:7)
    Correspondence concerning Sir Edmund Plowden research.
  - Lucy Drucker correspondence, 1937-1940., 109 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Correspondence and notes concerning Sir Edmund Plowden research.
  - Margaret Franklin correspondence, 1965-1966., 16 items. (Folder 1:9)
    Correspondence and notes concerning Plowden family genealogy.
  - Peter Guilday and William Keller correspondence, 1941-1960., 15 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Correspondence and notes concerning Keller's dissertation on Sir Edmund Plowden.
  - Mary Hoss Headman correspondence, 1933-1937., 26 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Correspondence and notes concerning the New Albion settlement attempt.
  - F.H.T. Jervoise correspondence, 1939-1956., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Correspondence concerning Sir Thomas Jervoise.
  - Walter J. Kaye correspondence, 1934., 6 items. (Folder 1:13)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1927-1991., 2 folders (103 items) (Box-folder 1:14-1:15)
    Correspondence on various topics.
  - Philip C. Plowden correspondence, 1932-1969., 4 folders (140 items) (Folder 2:1-2:4)
    - Philip C. Plowden correspondence, 1932-1935., 38 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Philip C. Plowden correspondence, 1936-1939., 39 items. (Folder 2:2)
    - Philip C. Plowden correspondence, 1940-1959., 39 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Philip C. Plowden correspondence, 1960-1969., 24 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Hilda S. Reid correspondence, 1935-1936., 21 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
    Correspondence concerning the New Albion settlement attempt.
  - Financial records, 1933-1973., 31 items. (Folder 2:6)
    Contains correspondence and receipts related to research efforts.
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1940-1988., 71 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
    Contains items related to research interests, newspaper clippings, notes, and a 1989 Villanova University grade report.
- Research Notebooks, ca. 1930-1951., 8 folders. (Box-folder 2:8-3:6)
  These notebooks were used by Lewis to summarize or organize aspects of his research findings.
  - "1642-1648 America," ca. 1930., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:8)
  - "1648-1659 England," ca. 1930., 1 item. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - "Beauchamp Plantagenet," 1951., 41 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
    Research compilation and related notes and correspondence.
  - "A direction for adventurers and a description of the province of New Albion.", 2 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - "Directions for adventurers.", 15 items. (Folder 3:3)
    Research compilation and related manuscripts copies and notes.
  - "Notes on Sir Edmund Plowden.", 1 item. (Folder 3:4)
  - "Plowden memorandum for Mr. Kaye," 1934., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:5)
  - "Some original records relating to Sir Edmund Plowden and his province of New Albion," ca. 1930., 1 item. (Folder 3:6)
- Photographs and Negatives, 1934-1993., 12 folders (122 items) (Box-folder 3:7-4:3)
  This series contains photographs and negatives of manuscripts Lewis was researching, including A Direction for Adventurers and "The Finest Part of America." It also contains images of locations such as Plowden Hall and Middle Temple Hall in England, Bushwood and Resurrection manors in Maryland, and of individuals including Lewis himself, and "Patrick and Rachel," surname unidentified.
  - 801 No. 64, 549 E. Herman, 1938., 15 items. (Folder 3:7)
  - Annotated Beauchamp Plantagenet., 15 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Bushwood, 1934., 16 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
  - "A direction for adventurers" and related manuscripts., 17 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Edmund Plowden's signature., 1 item. (Box-folder 3:11)
    Photographed from a 1641 document.
  - "The Finest part of America.", 16 items. (Folder 3:12)
    1784 document.
  - Middle Temple Hall, London, 1952., 3 items. (Box-folder 3:13)
  - People, 1986., 4 items. (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Plowden Hall and Vacation in England, 1937-ca. 1959., 35 items. (Folder 3:15)
  - Resurrection Manor, 1993., 58 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Unknown., 2 items. (Folder 4:2)
  - William Batt Letter., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
    Original letter dated 1656.
- Publications, 1937-1965., 10 folders (420 items) (Box-folder 4:4-4:13)
  Several publications emerged from Lewis' research. Copies of the publications, related correspondence and notes for the following publications by Lewis: "Some Notes on Sir Edmund Plowden and his Province of New Albion" (c.1937); an entry for the Dictionary of American History titled "Plowden's New Albion" (1938); "Some Extracts Relating to Sir Edmund Plowden and Others from the Lost Minutes of the Virginia Council and General Court 1642-1645" in the William and Mary Historical Quarterly (January 1940); a talk to the Numismatic and Antiquarian Society titled "Plowden's New Albion" (c.1956); "Sir Edmund Plowden and the New Albion Charter, 1632-1782" in The Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography" (April 1959).
  - "Plowden's New Albion" for the Dictionary of American History, 1937-1946., 26 items. (Folder 4:4)
    Includes correspondence and advertisements for the Dictionary.
  - "Plowden's New Albion" for the Dictionary of American History, 1937-1940., 11 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
    Draft copies.
  - "Plowden's New Albion: a talk to the Numismatic and Antiquarian Society," 1956., 2 items. (Box-folder 4:6)
    Draft of the address.
  - "Sir Edmund Plowden and the New Albion Charter, 1632-1782," an offprint from The Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, 1959., 7 items. (Folder 4:7)
    Copy of offprint, drafts.
  - "Sir Edmund Plowden and the New Albion Charter, 1632-1782," an offprint from The Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography, 1959-1965., 60 items. (Box-folder 4:8)
    Contains correspondence and notes.
  - "Some extracts relating to Sir Edmund Plowden and others from the Lost minutes of the Virginia Council and General Court, 1642-1645" in the William and Mary Quarterly, 1940., 7 items. (Folder 4:9)
    Reprints of publication, drafts.
  - Correspondence concerning: "Some extracts relating to Sir Edmund Plowden and others from the Lost minutes of the Virginia Council and General Court, 1642-1645," 1939-July 1940., 125 items. (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Correspondence concerning: "Some extracts relating to Sir Edmund Plowden and others from the Lost minutes of the Virginia Council and General Court, 1642-1645," 1940-1953., 97 items. (Box-folder 4:11)
  - "Some notes on Sir Edmund Plowden and his Province of New Albion," ca. 1937., 1 item. (Folder 4:12)
    Draft copy.
  - "Some notes on Sir Edmund Plowden and his Province of New Albion," 1937-1943., 22 items. (Folder 4:13)
    Correspondence and notes.
- Research Materials., 59 folders. (Box-folder 5:1-9:10)
  Research materials concern Sir Edmund Plowden (1590-1659), a member of the English aristocracy who was granted a charter in the seventeenth century to colonize present day Maryland, Delaware, and New York, an area Plowden called New Albion; also research covers colonial Maryland's history; the geography of the Middle Atlantic; the genealogy of the Plowdens and related families from the seventeenth century to the end of the twentieth century.
  - Research on Archbishop Carroll and Father Charles Plowden, 1975., 17 items. (Box-folder 5:1)
    Correspondence, notes and a brochure.
  - Research on Batchelor's Hope, 1985-1990., 2 items. (Box-folder 5:2)
    Articles.
  - Research on books and libraries, 1937-1956., 90 items. (Box-folder 5:3)
    Correspondence, notes and library publications.
  - Research on books and libraries and the Virginia Colonial Records Project, 1955-1957., 16 items. (Box-folder 5:4)
    Finding aid and survey reports.
  - Research on Bushwood. 1933-1986., 69 items. (Box-folder 5:5)
    Correspondence, notes and articles.
  - Research on Bysshe, Plowden's Irish title, 1881-1935., 4 items. (Box-folder 5:6)
    Notes and articles.
  - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, 1937-1980., 8 folders. (Folder 5:7-6:2)
    Correspondence, notes, articles and photostats.
    - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, 1951-1971., 21 items. (Folder 5:7)
      Correspondence: "Beauchamp Plantagenet's identity."
    - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, 1938-April 1939., 155 items. (Box-folder 5:8)
      Correspondence: "English search."
    - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, May-August 1939., 74 items. (Folder 5:9)
    - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, 1937-1980., 59 items. (Folder 5:10)
      Correspondence: "Successful."
    - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, March-May 1938., 62 items. (Box-folder 5:11)
      Correspondence: "Failures."
    - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, 1938-1939., 103 items. (Box-folder 6:1)
    - Research on A description of the Province of New Albion by Beauchamp Plantagenet, 1964., 18 items. (Box-folder 6:2)
      Photostat copy of Description and related articles and notes.
  - Research on the Eltonhead family, 1935-1965., 20 items. (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Research on English records, 1937-1964., 58 items. (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Research on a Georgetown University gift, 1935-1955., 32 items. (Box-folder 6:5)
    Correspondence, reports and notes.
  - Research on Thomas Gerard, 1935-1959., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:6)
    Article and notes.
  - Research on the Indian tribes of New Albion, 1945-1979., 14 items. (Box-folder 6:7)
    Draft article by C.A. Weslager, correspondence and notes.
  - Research on Irish records, 1939-1964., 31 items. (Folder 6:8)
  - Research on Sir Thomas Jervoise, 1651., 2 items. (Box-folder 6:9)
    Court records.
  - Research on maps, 1934-1966. (Box-folder 6:10-6:11)
    Correspondence, maps, articles and notes.
    - Research on maps, 1934-1966. (Folder 6:10)
      Correspondence.
    - Research on maps, 1924-1964., 24 items. (Box-folder 6:11)
      Maps, articles and notes.
  - Research on Martin's Hundred, 1979-1980., 14 items. (Box-folder 6:12)
    Correspondence and articles.
  - Research on Maryland church records, 1968-1973., 22 items. (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Research on Maryland Historical Magazine query responses, 1940-1941., 20 items. (Folder 6:14)
  - Research on Maryland records, 1938-1960., 17 items. (Box-folder 6:15)
  - Research on Maryland tourism, 1975., 14 items. (Box-folder 1975.)
    Maps and brochures.
  - Research on Edward D. Neill, 4 items. (Box-folder 7:1)
    Articles and notes.
  - Research on the New Albion boundary, 1965., 4 items. (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Research on the New Albion charter, 1933-1974., 78 items. (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Research on the New Albion petition, 5 items. (Box-folder 7:4)
    Notes.
  - Research on a New Albion spoon, 1887. (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Research on New Jersey records, 1940-1964., 19 items. (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Research on New Netherlands and New York records, 1936-1965., 29 items. (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Research on newspapers., 15 items. (Box-folder 7:8)
  - Research note cards., 52 items. (Folder 7:9)
  - Research on Plowden genealogy, 1767-1995., 6 folders. (Box-folder 7:10-8:1)
    Copies of articles, bible records, correspondence, notes, pedigree charts and reports.
    - Research on Plowden genealogy, 1767-1975., 45 items. (Box-folder 7:10)
      Photocopies of articles.
    - Research on Plowden genealogy, 1972., 5 items. (Box-folder 7:11)
      Bible records.
    - Research on Plowden genealogy, 1933-1995., 73 items. (Folder 7:12)
    - Research on Plowden genealogy, 1934-1987., 41 items. (Folder 7:13)
    - Research on Plowden genealogy, 41 items. (Box-folder 7:14)
      Pedigree charts.
    - Research on Plowden genealogy, 1933-1935., 16 items. (Folder 8:1)
      Reports.
  - Research on Plowden manuscripts, 1965-1966., 35 items. (Folder 8:2)
    Correspondence, notes and photocopies of manuscripts.
  - Research: Plowden notes., 3 items. (Folder 8:3)
  - Research on Sir Edmund Plowden, 1804-1991. (Box-folder 8:4-8:6)
    Articles, correspondence, notes and reports.
    - Research on Sir Edmund Plowden, 1804-1972., 16 items. (Box-folder 8:4)
    - Research on Sir Edmund Plowden, 1933-1991., 69 items. (Box-folder 8:5)
    - Research on Sir Edmund Plowden, 1804-1972., 68 items. (Box-folder 8:6)
      Notes and reports.
  - Research on Plowden's Commentaries, 1815-1939., 5 items. (Folder 8:7)
  - Research on Resurrection Manor, 1992-1993., 26 items. (Box-folder 8:8)
    Correspondence, articles and notes.
  - Research on St. Mary's County, Maryland, 1959-1989., 30 items. (Box-folder 9:1)
    Brochures, maps, guides and correspondence.
  - Research on the settlers and partners of New Albion, 1940-1953., 77 items. (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Research on "Sir Edmund Plowden's New Albion (1632-1650) revisited," 1989., 2 items. (Folder 9:3)
    Graduate school term paper.
  - Research on Sotterly, 1934-1994., 10 items. (Box-folder 9:4)
    Articles and correspondence.
  - Research on the Strafford Papers, 1938., 7 items. (Box-folder 9:5)
  - Research on the Streeter Clairborne manuscript, 1934-1966., 31 items. (Box-folder 9:6)
    Correspondence, notes and a photocopy of a manuscript.
  - Research on Swedish records, 1934-1940., 22 items. (Folder 9:7)
  - Research on Thomas Varlo, 1933-1939., 32 items. (Box-folder 9:8)
  - Research on Virginia records, 1934-1956., 43 items. (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Research on Thomas Young and Robert Evelin, 1944-1960., 51 items. (Box-folder 9:10)
- Oversize Materials., 134 items. (Box 10)
  Contains 66 maps of Virginia, Maryland, Delaware, and New York; 38 genealogical tables of the Plowden and Lewis families; 27 reproductions of manuscripts; 2 reproductions of portraits of Sir Edmund Plowden; and 1 article.